SAQIB ARFEEN

Berlin, Germany

sagib.arfeen@gmail.com | github.com/sagibarfeen | linkedIn.com/in/mohamedsagib

SUMMARY

Software engineer • Backend engineer • Data engineer

Software Engineer with 7 years of specialised experience in SaaS, No-code, ERP, Cloud, and Big Data. Known for deep technical expertise and leading research initiatives that resulted in groundbreaking methodologies.

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: JavaScript, TypeScript, C++, Java, Python, Go
- Programming Frameworks: Spring, Express, React, Netsuite SuiteCloud Platform, Nvidia CUDA
- Databases: Postgres, MySQL, MongoDB, ElasticSearch, Graphite, InfluxDB, Hadoop, Spark, Ninox
- Cloud & Distributed Systems: OpenStack, AWS Lambda EC2 EKS SQS SES, Hadoop MapReduce, Kafka, RabbitMQ, Redis
- SRE/DevOps: Kubernetes, Prometheus, CI/CD with Circle CI and Github Actions, Ansible, Puppet, Nagios, Icinga
- Data Visualisation: Grafana, Kibana

EXPERIENCE

Ninox Software GmbH (ninox.com), Berlin

Nov 2022 – Present

Senior Software Engineer

- Contributed to engineering high-impact features that elevated product competitiveness and quality, correlating with a growth of 25% in ARR.
- Conceptualised and prototyped software architectures, effectively bridging technical possibilities with product vision through close collaboration with product owners.

Seed Labs, Karachi

Oct 2021 – Sep 2022

Senior Software Engineer

- Designed and implemented a robust persistence and fault-tolerance mechanism using Kafka, elevating system resilience and data integrity.
- Achieved a 10 fold reduction in the build times.
- Instrumented and optimised critical backend components, including the order-matching engine and blockchain settlement engine of a Decentralised exchange (DEX).
- Executed a strategic migration to Kubernetes, resulting in an 70% reduction in fixed infrastructure costs, enhancing scalability and operational efficiency.

Folio3 Software Inc, Karachi

Nov 2019 – Sep 2021

- As a Senior Engineer on the Netsuite ERP team, spearheaded the development of business process customisations and integrations, delivering high-quality projects that fostered long-term partnerships with multiple Fortune 500 companies.
- Initiated and curated an in-house knowledge base focused on ERP design patterns and business workflows, resulting in a 50% reduction in development costs for routine projects.

Ivolve Technologies, Karachi

Jun 2019 - Nov 2019

Senior Software Engineer

- Spearheaded the recruitment and training initiatives to successfully transition product development from an outsourced model to an in-house team. Achieved increased operational agility and reduced time-to-market.
- Orchestrated the integration of OpenStack with multiple cloud services, creating a versatile, hybrid-cloud middleware solution that enhanced infrastructure flexibility.
- Designed and executed a robust OpenStack usage calculation and billing system by seamlessly integrating a suite of specialised tools including Ceilometer, Gnocchi, ElasticSearch, and Grafana. This end-to-end solution streamlined cloud management, facilitated accurate usage tracking.

Cloud 9 Networks, Karachi

July 2016 – May 2019

Software Engineer

- Spearheaded the architecture, development, and deployment of a big-data software solution for a customer loyalty card payment system in the MENA region.
- Engineered the research, design, and rollout of diverse SaaS products, such as B2B Business Intelligence tools, OpenStack cloud monitoring systems, and network infrastructure monitors, showcasing a keen focus on end-to-end product delivery.
- Accelerated development timelines, delivering products in weekly cycles instead of monthly sprints, maximising efficiency and resource utilisation. e.g bit.ly/siem-saqib
- Orchestrated comprehensive training programs for incoming developers, expediting their transition to productive engineering roles within the company.
- Identified market opportunities, conceptualised and executed a new product in Actionable Intelligence for IT, securing a significant contract from a top-tier telecom provider in Pakistan.

EDUCATION

BS, Computer Science CGPA: 3.03/4.0

FAST National University of Computer and Emerging Sciences, Karachi Registration No. 12K-2322

CERTIFICATIONS

- Coursera: The Data Scientist's Toolbox (CZ4FS4J6T972)
- Coursera: <u>AI for Everyone</u> (F926BXSQE638)
- Coursera: <u>Tensorflow on Google Cloud</u> (KJ3QWPW3FJUT)
- Coursera: IBM Cloud Private: Deploying Microservices with Kubernetes (LD83GGMJ84L5)
- Coursera: Neural Networks and Deep Learning (UMRA4C82PK8V)